{"tossups": [{"question": "A boy named Chanco saved this city from a native raid by warning his caregiver, Richard Pace, of the impending attack. In the opening days of the Civil War, William Allen raised a private pro-Confederate militia to occupy this site to block the Union from reaching Richmond downstream. This city was partially razed in the midst of Bacon's Rebellion, and the House of Burgesses was originally set up in this settlement prior to its relocation to Williamsburg. A Stuart king names, for ten points, which first permanent English settlement in North America?", "answer": "<b><u>Jamestown</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "All three daughters of one ruler of this name were accused of adultery in the Tour de Nesle [NEH-luh]] Affair. One ruler of this name sent his son Louis to go on the Albigensian Crusade. That ruler with this name crushed the English at the Battle of Bouvines [[boo-VEEN]]. A Spanish ruler of this name invaded the Netherlands in the Eighty Years\u2019 War, and that ruler of this name formed a fleet with the aim of deposing Elizabeth I that was defeated at Gravelines [[grav-LEEN]]. For ten points, give this name of the king who created the Spanish Armada.", "answer": "<b><u>Philip</u></b> (accept <b><u>Philip</u></b> IV; accept <b><u>Philip</u></b> II of France; accept <b><u>Philip II</u></b> of Spain; accept <b><u>Felipe</u></b> or <b><u>Philippe</u></b> in place of <b><u>Philip</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The Black Panthers inspired a party composed and named for this group which led a renaissance of Maharashtra-based literature and fine arts in the 1970s. The term <em>Harijan</em>, which translates to \"Children of God,\" was used to refer to this group of people in the early 20th century. Under the influence of Rajiv Gandhi, one parliament passed the Prevention of Atrocities Act in an attempt to halt discrimination against this class of people. Mohandas Gandhi was an advocate for, for ten points, which ostracized class of the Indian caste system?", "answer": "<b><u>Untouchable</u></b>s (accept the <b><u>Dalit</u></b>s; accept the <b><u>Scheduled</u></b> Caste; accept the <b><u>Dalit</u> </b>Panthers)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A crossbowmen who may have practiced this discipline shot and killed Richard the Lionheart during a siege of Chalus in France. Caelius Apicius [[ah-PIH-kee-us]] wrote a work in this field in Vulgar Latin which opens with the chapter <em>Epimeles</em>, or \"The Careful Housekeeper.\" Gervase Markham wrote a work in this discipline named <em>The English</em> <em>Housewife</em>, including a chapter titled \"Banqueting Stuff.\" <em>De re culinaria</em> is a pamphlet on, for ten points, what discipline which involves preparing food?", "answer": "<b><u>Cook</u></b>ing (accept <b><u>Gastronomy</u></b>; accept <b><u>Culinary</u></b> arts before \"culinaria\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s body was allegedly placed in a glass coffin, but a team of forensic scientists discovered it was incorrectly identified. After this man executed the loser of the Battle of Cajamarca [[kah-hah-MAHR-kah]], this man had two sons with his widow, renamed Dona Angelina. This man\u2019s life ended when supporters of Diego de Almagro's son stormed a palace and assassinated him, making Almagro the new Governor of Peru. For ten points, name this conquistador who founded Lima after destroying the Inca Empire.", "answer": "Francisco <b><u>Pizarro</u></b> (or Francisco <b><u>Pizarro</u></b> Gonz\u00e1lez)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Queen Elizabeth II granted this title to Margot Fonteyn after her performance as the Queen of Air in <em>Homage to the Queen</em>. Following an international tour with the Kirov company, American Eva Evdokimova [[ehv-DOH-kee-MOH-vah]] was given the <em>assoluta</em> form of this designation. The solo dance known as <em>The Dying Swan</em> was originated by a person with this specific designation, Anna Pavlova, who held the title while a member of Ballet Russes [[ROOSE]]. The most talented and experienced ballet dancers in a company are given, for ten points, which designation?", "answer": "<b><u>Prima ballerina</u></b> (prompt on partial answers; accept <b><u>Prima ballerina</u></b> assoluta)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Dance"}, {"question": "This thinker was invited to a feast by Emperor Frederick II, to whom this man dedicated his <em>Book of Squares</em>. For his technical work, like solving several problems by Johannes of Palermo, this man was granted a lifetime salary by his home city of Pisa. This man's work <em>Liber Abaci</em> popularized Indo-Arabic numerals in the western world, as well as a biologically relevant namesake series of numbers. For ten points, name this medieval Italian mathematician whose namesake \"sequence\" begins, \"0, 1, 1, 2, 3.\"", "answer": "<b><u>Fibonacci</u></b> (accept <b><u>Leonardo Bonacci</u></b>; or <b><u>Leonardo of Pisa</u></b>; or <b><u>Leonardo</u></b> <b><u>Bigano Pisano</u></b>; accept <b><u>Fibonacci</u></b> Numbers; or <b><u>Fibonacci</u></b> Sequence)", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Math"}, {"question": "This man publicly protested segregation by sharing a small pool with an African-American character, Officer Clemmons, in a 1969 episode of his namesake series. This man quoted that show by saying \"What Do You Do with the Mad that You Feel?\" in an argument to save funding for PBS while testifying in front of the Senate Subcommittee of Communications in 1969. The opening theme \"Won't You Be My Neighbor?\" was written by, for ten points, which host of a long-running children's TV show about [this man's] <em>Neighborhood</em>?", "answer": "Fred <b><u>Rogers</u></b> (accept Mister <b><u>Rogers</u></b>; accept <em><b><u>Mister Rogers'</u></b> Neighborhood</em>)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "During this event, the generals Aleksei Peshchurov [[pehsh-CHOO-roff]] and Lovell Rousseau oversaw a flag transfer ceremony in the town of New Archangel. The extinction of a local sea otter population and the monetary deficit experienced after the Crimean War led to this event, which was negotiated by Eduard de Stoeckl [[STOW-kuhl]]. Detractors of this action dubbed it both \"Seward's Icebox\" and \"Seward's Folly.\" For ten points, name this acquisition by the Andrew Johnson administration of a Russian colony in North America.", "answer": "<b><u>Alaska Purchase</u></b> (or <b><u>Purchase</u></b> of <b><u>Alaska</u></b>; accept synonymous answers like <b><u>Buy</u></b>ing <b><u>Alaska</u></b>; accept <b><u>Prodazha Alyaski</u></b>; or <b><u>Sale</u></b> of <b><u>Alaska</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In a work in this language, the <em>eardstapa</em>, or \"Wanderer,\" is in self-imposed exile after losing his lord and fellow retainers during a raid. The long form poem <em>The Age of Anxiety</em> by W.H. Auden is in this specific language, emulating an early style of alliterative verse. The limbs of a monster named Grendel are taken off in a mead hall by the title hero of an epic poem in this language. The poem <em>Beowulf</em> is written in, for ten points, which medieval language of the British isles influenced by Old Norse?", "answer": "<b><u>Old English</u></b> (accept <b><u>Anglo-Saxon</u></b>; accept <b><u>Englis\u010b</u></b>; prompt on \"English\"; do not accept \"Middle English\")", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "This president repealed the Glass-Steagall Act, citing it was \"no longer appropriate.\" This president signed a law mandating background checks on firearms purchases, the Brady Bill, and dealt with \"Troopergate\" when several officers from his home state alleged they had arranged romantic liaisons for him. This president's Whitewater scandals merged with another scandal in which he claimed to have not had \"sexual relations with that woman.\" For ten points, name this Democratic president during the 1990s who was impeached for perjury for lying about his affair with Monica Lewinsky.", "answer": "Bill <b><u>Clinton</u></b> (or William Jefferson <b><u>Clinton</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Excessive flooding in this city in 1927 led to the training ship known as the <em>President</em> to float down its streets. The use of low quality coal and the occurrence of an \"anticyclone\" led to the 1952 \"Great Smog\" in this city, killing 4,000 people. Three disease outbreaks were studied by John Snow in this city during its \"Great Stink\" period. A buildup of waste on the Thames [[TEMZ]] occurred in, for ten points, which English capital?", "answer": "<b><u>London</u></b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "A monarch from this dynasty patronized the <em>Fatawa 'Alamgiri</em> law code as part of a personal religious revival that included becoming a <em>hafiz</em>. This dynasty, which was the last regime to destroy the Vishwanath Temple, scaled back religious tolerance by executing Tegh Bahadur, a Sikh guru, and reinstituting the <em>jizya</em> tax under its emperor Aurangzeb. For ten points, name this Muslim dynasty that ruled north India following the 1520s conquests of Babur.", "answer": "<b><u>Mughal</u></b> Dynasty (or the <b><u>Mughal</u></b>s)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This man earned the ire of the internet after a tweet resurfaced of him saying, \"Nothing sadder than a hot person in a wheelchair\" in reference to disability activist Rebecca Cokely. After a streak of early 2000s television appearances, this man was approached by Harry Reid and Chuck Schumer to run for the U.S. Senate from Utah. This man defeated both Brad Rutter and James Holzhauer in a special tournament dubbed \"The Greatest of All Time.\" The longest streak in <em>Jeopardy!</em> history is held by, for ten points, which game show contestant?", "answer": "Ken <b><u>Jennings</u></b> (or Kenneth Wayne <b><u>Jennings</u></b> III)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "During the first Easter festivities celebrated on Cebu [[SEE-boo]], this European formed a blood compact with the local tribal head, Rajah Humabon. Legendarily, Chief Lapu-Lapu slew this man with a traditional bolo knife during the Battle of Mactan. This man, who sailed under the Spanish flag, named the Pacific Ocean in the 1520s while leading an expedition to the East Indies. For ten points, name this Portuguese explorer whose crew completed the first circumnavigation of the globe.", "answer": "Ferdinand <b><u>Magellan</u></b> (accept Fern\u00e3o de <b><u>Magalh\u00e3es</u></b>; or Fernando de <b><u>Magallan</u></b>es)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The American company Hobby Lobby illegally purchased artifacts from this modern nation through dealers in the United Arab Emirates to populate their Museum of the Bible. Archeologist Gertrude Bell first excavated the Al-Ukhaidir [[ook-\"HIGH\"-deer]] Fortress in this nation, which was built by Caliph Isa ibn Musa to defend the Abbasid city of Karbala. The World Heritage site known as Ashur lies in, for ten points, which modern nation of the Middle East, governed from Baghdad?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Iraq</u></b> (accept Jumh\u016bri\u012byah al-<b><u>\u02bfIr\u0101q</u></b>; or Komar\u00ee <b><u>\u00caraq</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Many performers in these productions, which had a second-act <em>olio</em>, cribbed material from a New Orleans vendor named Old Corn Meal. Fixed roles in these productions included Mr. Tambo, Mr. Bones, and the interlocutor. A popular group that staged these productions was named for Edwin Pearce Christy and incorporated the music of Stephen Foster. For ten points, name this genre of racially charged 19th-century live variety shows in which performers often wore blackface.", "answer": "<b><u>Minstrel</u></b> shows (or <b><u>minstrel</u></b>sy; prompt on \"blackface shows\" before \"blackface\" is mentioned)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Misc Arts"}, {}, {"question": "It's not alchemists, but people of this profession were rounded up and killed by Louis XIV's officials during the Affair of the Poisons. It's not magicians, but escape-artist Harry Houdini undertook a campaign funded by the <em>Scientific American</em> to debunk these figures. The Pythia was a priestess of Apollo who specifically did this job. Pliny the Elder is the first historian to mention the use of a crystal ball used by magi in this position. The use of divination is done by, for ten points, what specific people who claim to prophesize the future?", "answer": "<b><u>Fortune-Tellers</u></b> (accept <b><u>Psychic</u></b>s; or <b><u>Medium</u></b>s; or <b><u>Oracle</u></b>s; accept descriptions of people with <b><u>precognition</u></b> or the ability to <b><u>see the future</u></b>; prompt on \"Witches\")  The Pythia served as the head of an Oracle in which Phocian city considered the center of the Earth by the Ancient Greeks?  ANSWER: <b><u>Delphi</u></b> (accept <b><u>Pytho</u></b>)  <b> </b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "<b><u>A false bomb threat was leveraged by this national government to arrest</u></b> <b><u>dissident journalist Raman Pratasevich in June 2021. Opposition leader Sergei (+)</u></b> <b>Tikhanovsky [[teek-hah-NOHV-skee]] was sentenced to jail for eighteen years in response to his plan to challenge a president of this country seeking his sixth term. The Anti-Cockroach Movement opposed longtime president Alexander (*) </b>Lukashenko [[loo-kah-SHEN-koh]] in, for ten points, what Eastern European nation governed from Minsk?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Belarus</u></b> (or Respublika <b><u>Belarus</u></b>; accept <b><u>Byelorussia</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b>This </b> <b>man </b> <b>first </b> <b>led </b> <b>the </b> <b>\"Radical </b> <b>Division\" </b> <b>during </b> <b>the </b> <b>Palmer </b> <b>Raids </b> <b><u> and had a public dispute with T.R.M. Howard over the lethargic (+)</u> police response to Southern lynchings. Starting in 1956, this man authorized a wide-ranging program of partially illegal infiltration and disinformation called (*) </b>COINTELPRO [[koh-IHN-tel-pro]], which targeted the Black Panthers and Martin Luther King. For ten points, name this man who served from 1924 to his 1972 death as the director of the FBI and its precursors.", "answer": "J. Edgar <b><u>Hoover</u></b> (or John Edgar <b><u>Hoover</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Position and nation required</u></b></em><b><u>. During the Hague Secret Emissary Affair, the last</u></b> <b><u>man in this position attempted to assert his right to sovereign diplomacy despite its</u></b> <b><u>official loss in the Eulsa Treaty of 1905. This position is symbolically represented by</u></b> <b><u>the Phoenix (+)</u> Throne, and it was legendarily established by Dangun according to the </b><em><b>Gogi</b></em><b> [[GOH-gee]]. The </b><em><b>hangul</b></em><b> (*) </b>writing system was invented by a man in this position named Sejong the Great. For ten points, name this regal position held for five centuries by the Joseon Dynasty.", "answer": "<b><u>Monarch</u></b> of <b><u>Korea</u></b> (accept <b><u>Ruler</u></b>, <b><u>King</u></b>, or <b><u>Emperor</u></b> in place of \"Monarch\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In Medieval England, the eggs of this specific animal were fed to children to</u></b> <b><u>ward off drunkenness and as a cure to blindness. One of these animals named Ko'Ko,</u></b> <b><u>or the \"Watcher of the dark,\" is the underworld deity of the Hopi. A contingent of this</u></b> <b><u>specific bird flying over the battle site of (+)</u> Salamis signaled a Greek victory over the Persians according to Plutarch. The Athenian </b><em><b>tetradrachma</b></em><b> depicts this (*) </b>bird and symbol of the city on its backside. For ten points, name this bird which symbolized wisdom in Ancient Greece and is associated with Athena.", "answer": "<b><u>Owl</u></b>s (or <b><u>Strigiform</u></b>es; accept Athene <b><u>noctua</u></b>; or <b><u>Owl</u></b> of Athena; accept <b><u>Owl</u></b> of Minerva; prompt on \"birds\" or \"avians\")", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "<b><u>In this city, a man who removed his shoes to reveal black socks wore a beaded</u></b> <b><u>necklace representing victims of lynching and the slave trade. An event in this city was</u></b> <b><u>planned by the (+)</u> OPHR, an organization co-founded by Harry Edwards. Wearing black gloves, Tommie Smith and John Carlos made a raised-fist gesture in this city while \"The Star-Spangled Banner\" played. American and Australian athletes displayed Black Power (*) </b>symbols at the 1968 Summer Olympics held in, for ten points, what capital city?", "answer": "<b><u>Mexico City</u></b> (accept <b><u>Ciudad de M\u00e9xico</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man wrote a romanticized account of the Covenanters victory at Loudon</u></b> <b><u>Hill in his novel</u> </b><em><b><u>Old Mortality</u></b></em><b><u>. The lynching of the title man in the historical Porteous</u></b> <b><u>[[POHR-shus]] Riots in Edinburgh acts as the backdrop for this man's novel, (+)</u> </b><em><b>The </b><b>Heart of the Midlothian</b></em><b>. In another novel by this man, the title Anglo-Saxon pretends to be the Spanish knight </b><em><b>Desdichado</b></em><b> to win a (*) </b>tournament presided over by King John. Rowena is married to the title knight at the behest of Richard the Lionheart in, for ten points, what author's novel <em>Ivanhoe</em>?", "answer": "Walter <b><u>Scott</u></b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "<b><u>Johann Gustav Droysen wrote the seven volume work</u> </b><em><b><u>The History of [this</u></b></em> <em><b><u>state's] Politics</u></b></em><b><u> and led it's namesake school of historiography in the 19th century. The</u></b> <b><u>treatise</u> </b><em><b><u>On</u></b></em><b><u> (+)</u> </b><em><b>War</b></em><b> was written by a military theorist and general from this kingdom, Carl von Clausewitz. Count Mirabeau [[me-rah-BOH]] once stated this kingdom was \"not a state with a (*) </b>military, but a military with a state.\" For ten points, name this early modern state which united Germany in the 19th century under the leadership of Otto von Bismarck.", "answer": "Kingdom of <b><u>Prussia</u></b> (or K\u00f6nigreich <b><u>Preussen</u></b>; prompt on \"Germany\" or \"German Empire\" before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>While in prison for supposedly perpetrating this violent event, German-</u><u>American Louis Lingg killed himself with a blast cap hidden in a cigar rather than going</u></b> <b><u>to trial. Men arrested during this event are labelled (+)</u> \"Mad Dogs\" in a contemporary political cartoon where they attack a personification of the U.S. after being set free by Governor John Altgeld. Albert Parsons claimed a Pinkerton agent threw the (*) </b>dynamite which began this violent labor demonstration. Agitation for the eight-hour workday led to violence in, for ten points, what Chicago riot of the late 1880s?", "answer": "<b><u>Haymarket</u></b> Square Riot (accept <b><u>Haymarket</u></b> Affair; or <b><u>Haymarket</u></b> Massacre)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This nation's Bureau 39 smuggled in a printing press from Japan to produce so-</u><u>called \"Superdollars,\" which were perfect replicas of American 100 dollar bills. The</u></b> <b><u>Donghak movement of the 19th century birthed a minority party in this nation called</u></b> <b><u>the Chondoist (+)</u> Chongu Party, which control six seats in the Supreme People's Assembly. This nation is governed by a coalition named the Democratic Front for the Reunification of the Fatherland, which aims to conquer a southern (*) </b>neighbor. For ten points, name this Communist state whose government is centered on Pyongyang.", "answer": "<b><u>North Korea</u></b> (accept <b><u>DPRK</u></b> or the <b><u>Democratic People's Republic of Korea</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}